# Samuel V. Hulse

Postdoctral Associate Theoretical Evolutionary Biologist

Address: Phone: (443) 527-5710)
1350 Shepherd St NW Email: shulse@umd.edu

Washington, DC 20011 GitHub: svhulse

## **Professional Interests**

For my doctoral work, I focused on expanding the domain of the sensory drive model beyond peripheral sensory processing, to explain the evolution of complex visual displays. In the Bruns Lab, I am working to develop theoretical models for how evolutionary feedbacks influence disease resistance in plant models. My understanding of the field has been greatly informed by my passion for mathematics, and I am captivated by how evolutionary theory can be made more rigorous through interdisciplinary approaches.

# **Professional Experience**

#### 2021 - Curr. Postdoctoral Associate

University of Maryland College Park, Baltimore, MD

Supervisor: Dr. Emily Bruns

## **Education**

#### 2021 Ph.D., Biological Sciences

University of Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD

Dissertation: The Evolution of Visual Patterning in North American Freshwater Fishes

Supervisor: Dr. Tamra Mendelson

#### 2021 M.S., Applied Mathematics

University of Maryland Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD

#### 2012 B.S., Environmental Science

Juniata College, Huntingdon, PA

### **Publications**

#### Peer-Reviewed Publications

**Hulse, S.V.,** Antonovics, J., Hood, M.E., and Bruns, E.L. Host-pathogen coevolution promotes the evolution of general, broad-spectrum resistance and reduces foreign pathogen spillover risk.

Accepted, Evolution Letters.

2023

<b>Hulse, S.V.,</b> Antonovics, J., Hood, M.E., and Bruns, E.L. Specific resistance prevents the evolution of general resistance and facilitates disease emergence. <i>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</i> 36: 753-763.
<b>Hulse, S.V.,</b> Renoult, J.P., and Mendelson, T.C. Using deep neural networks to model similarity between visual patterns: Application to fish sexual signals. <i>Ecological Informatics</i> 67: 101486.
<b>Hulse, S.V.,</b> Renoult, J.P., and Mendelson, T.C. Sexual signaling pattern correlates with habitat pattern in visually ornamented fishes. <i>Nature Communications</i> 11: 2561.
Dissertation
Hulse, S.V. The Evolution of Visual Patterning in North American Freshwater Fishes.
Conferences and Presentations
Invited Talks
<b>Hulse, S.V.</b> The evolution and maintenance of host genetic diversity for pathogen resistance. Mathematical Biology Seminar, University of Maryland College Park.
<b>Hulse, S.V.</b> Applications of Deep Learning to Fish Behavioral Patterns. Machine Learners Group Seminar, Scripps Institution of Oceanography.
<b>Hulse, S.V.</b> Understanding the signals animals send each other. High School Assembly Presentation, The Park School of Baltimore.
Contributed Talks
<b>Hulse</b> , <b>S.V.</b> A theoretical model for the shape of evolutionary tradeoffs. Southeastern Population Ecology and Evolutionary Genetics, Pembroke, VA.
<b>Hulse, S.V.</b> The role of coevolution in mantaining host resistance structures. Evolution, Albuquerque, NM.
<b>Hulse, S.V.</b> Does host-pathogen coevolution increase the risk of foreign pathogen invasion? Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases, State College, PA.
<b>Hulse, S.V.</b> Visual statistsics of habitat predict spatial aspect of visual signals. University of Maryland Behavior, Ecology, Evolution, and Systematics Department Retreat, Thurmont, MD.
Mendelson, T.C., <b>Hulse, S.V.,</b> Renoult, J.P. Complex nuptial patterns of fish species mimic the spatial statistics of their habitat. Annual meeting of the Animal Behavior Society, Chicago, IL.
Hulse, S.V. The Efficient Coding Hypothesis and Signal Design. UMBC Biological Sciences

Hulse, S.V., and Mendelson, T.C. The efficient coding hypothesis and signal design. Annual

meeting of the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, San Francisco, CA.

Departmental Seminar, Baltimore, MD.

2017 Hulse, S.V., and Mendelson, T.C. The efficient coding hypothesis and signal design. Spotlight Talk, Evolution, Portland, OR. **Posters** 2022 Hulse, S.V., and Bruns. E.L. Disease Resistance at the Whole Organism Level, The Joint Evolution of General and Specific Resistance. Ecology and Evolution of Infectious Diseases, Atlanta GA. 2020 Hulse, S.V., Mendelson, T.C., and Renoult, J.P. The spatial statistics of sexual signals in fishes correspond to their habitat: extending sensory drive to signal design. NSF workshop: Biology through Information Communication Coding Theory, Alexandria, VA. Hulse, S.V., Renoult, J.P., and Mendelson, T.C. The Efficient Coding Hypothesis and the Evolu-2018 tion of Signal Design. Evolution, Montpellier, France. Hulse, S.V., and Mendelson, T.C. The efficient coding hypothesis and signal design. Annual 2017 meeting of the Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology, New Orleans, LA. Grants, Awards, and Fellowships **Fellowships** 2019 Millhauser Fellowship, The Park School of Baltimore (\$250) 2018 Chateaubriand Fellowship, The Embassy of France in the United States (\$4200) **Travel Awards** NSF BIOtIC Workshop Student Support (Housing Support) 2020 SICB Charlotte Magnum Student Support (Housing Support) 2018 2018 SICB Charlotte Magnum Student Support (Housing Support) Wilson Ornithological Society Travel Award (\$285) 2018 Other Awards 2018 AAAS/Science Program for Excellence in Science (Full AAAS Membership benefits) Training University of Maryland Mentoring Workshops for Postdoctoral Fellows, College Park, MD. 2022 2020 MIT Brains, Minds Machines Virtual Summer Course, Woods Hole, MA.

# **Teaching Experience**

2023 Developing Course: BSCI 338V: Introduction to Python for Life Sciences

2015-2021 Teaching Assistant, Comparative Vertebrate Physiology Lab

2016-2020 Teaching Assistant, Anatomy and Physiology II Lab

2018 Guest Lecturer, Sexual Selection2017, 2018 Guest Lecturer, Animal Behavior

# Mentoring

## **Undergraduate Mentoring, University of Maryland College Park**

2023 Molly Gans, Amherst University

2022 Daniel Fu, University of Maryland College Park

## **Academic Service**

# **Manuscript Peer Reviewed**

2023 Biology Letters (Joint review with Dr. Emily Bruns)

2022 Evolutionary Ecology2020 Behavioral Ecology

#### Misc. Service

2023 - Curr. Founder and Organiser: UMD Mathematical Biology Journal Club

2023 SSE W. D. Hamilton Award Judge

2023 Maryland Day 2023 Outreach Volunteer

2016-2020 UMBC Department of Biological Science FUN Committee

2016-2017 UMBC Graduate Student Association Senator